Dickey mss., 1872-1941 LMC 1312
Lilly Library
Dickey mss.
1872-1941
Lilly Library
Dickey, J. M. (John Marcus)
LMC 1312
12 Boxes 11 standard, 1 custom
The Dickey mss., 1872-1941, consists of the papers of John Marcus Dickey, 1859-1950, secretary, platform manager, and biographer of James Whitcomb Riley.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Acquisition Information
Acquired: 1951, 1956, 1961
Biographical Note
John Marcus Dickey, 1859-1950, was an American secretary, platform manager, and biographer of James Whitcomb Riley. He was born on September 26, 1859 near Longwood, Fayette County, Indiana. He attended the Indiana State Normal School, Terre Haute, Indiana, 1880-1883; taught history and literature at the Fairmont, Indiana Academy, 1887-1889; was principal of the public schools, Colorado Springs, Colorado, 1890-1892; was director of the Rocky Mountain Lyceum, Denver, Colorado, 1892-1896; and served James Whitcomb Riley as platform manager, 1896-1901, and as secretary, 1901-1906. From 1905 on he lived at Bear Wallow, Brown County, Indiana. His published works are Columbus and His Monument (1893); The Youth of James Whitcomb Riley (1919); The Maturity of James Whitcomb Riley (1922) and various articles in periodicals.
Scope and Content Note
The James Whitcomb Riley material in the collection includes tour receipts, 1897, 1898, 1899, 1900, 1901, and 1903; letters and copies of letters, 1901-1917, written by Dickey as Riley's secretary and biographer; manuscripts of writings of Dickey about Riley, including an early holograph draft and a revised typescript of The maturity of James Whitcomb Riley, a complete early holograph draft, a revised partial typescript (Chap. 1-17) and a later typescript of Chap. 18 only of The Youth of James Whitcomb Riley, a partial early draft and two later typescripts of Memories of James Whitcomb Riley, a holograph draft of the Orphant Annie book, five typescripts of Orphant Annie days, and miscellaneous articles; notes relating to Riley; letters written to Dickey, 1892-1925, primarily related to Dickey's search for material for Riley's biography; an undated Index to the Works of James Whitcomb Riley, by Katherine Josephine Dowling; and an undated bibliography of Riley's writings appearing in newspapers.
Other papers of Dickey in the collection include his diaries, 1885-1896 and 1908; a typescript of The Forest Life of Abraham Lincoln; three typescripts of The Light of Beacon Ridge; miscellaneous short writings; and scrapbooks.
Also included are autograph books 1872, 1878, and 1879, and scrapbooks of Isabelle E. (White) Dickey, and a Diary kept first time in crossing the ocean from Glasgow to New York, September 12-October 5, 1879, by J.A. Campbell.
Among the Miscellaneous items is a block of unfinished wood, 9 3/4 x 4 7/8 x 1 inches, on which is written in pencil in the hand of John Marcus Dickey a verse in the style of James Whitcomb Riley.
Authors, American--Correspondence; American Literature--Indiana; Riley, James Whitcomb, 1849-1916--Correspondence.; Riley, James Whitcomb, 1849-1916; Dickey, J. M. (John Marcus)--Correspondence.
- Collection (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1892 - Dec. 15, 1902 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, Dec. 26, 1902 - n.d. (Box 2)
  - Riley tour receipts, Oct. 1898 - 1901 (Box 2)
  - Riley tour receipts, Nov. 1898 - 1901 (Box 3)
  - Riley tour receipts, 1903 (Box 4)
  - Writings: (Box 4)
    - Orphant Annie Book (Box 4)
  - Writings: (Box 5)
    - The Maturity of J.W. Riley (Box 5)
    - Writings of J.W. Riley (Box 5)
  - Writings: (Box 6)
    - The Youth of J.W. Riley (Box 6)
    - A-Z (Box 6)
  - Misc. notebooks, scrapbooks. (Box 7)
  - Writings: (Box 7)
    - Memories 1 and 2 (Box 7)
  - Riley letters copied by Dickey. (Box 8)
  - Writings: (Box 8)
    - Forest Life (Box 8)
    - Light of Beacon Ridge (Box 8)
  - Pictures. (Box 9)
  - Notebooks (60) about Riley. (Box 10)
  - Annotated table of contents for The Youth of James Whitcomb Riley, (2 sets) (Box 10)
  - Contains 14 journals from 1879-1908, an undated journal, notebook from ca. 1907, and scrapbook from 1890s. (Box 11)
  - 4 photographs (Box 12)